HAIWEN DIAO

Three-year Doctoral Candidate

Intelligent Image Analysis and Understanding (IIAU) Lab School of Information and Communication Engineering Dalian University of Technology (DUT) No.2 Linggong Road, Dalian City, China, 116024

Address: Email: diaohw@mail.dlut.edu.cn \leq Homepage \leq Google Scholar

Research Interests

My primary research interests are *Vision-and-Language*, *Transfer Learning* and *Multimodal Large Language Model*. Specifically, my research in the vision-and-language domain strives to build up an efficient system that entails recognizing visual-semantic perception and contextualizing fine-grained correspondence across modalities.

Experience

Beijing Academy of Artificial Intelligence, Beijing

Sep.2023 — Present

Research Internship

• Director: Dr. XinLong Wang (Computer Vision Center)

Hong Kong University of Science and Technology, Dalian

Jan.2023 — Jul.2023

Remote Visiting Research

• Director: Dr. Long Chen (Computer Science and Engineering)

Tencent AI Lab, Shenzhen

Jun.2020 — Mar.2021

CCF-Tencent Open Fund

• Director: Dr. Ying Zhang, Dr. Lin Ma (Computer Vision Center)

Education

Dalian University of Technology (DUT), Dalian

Sep. 2021 — Present

Ph.D. in Information and Communication Engineering

- Thesis: Parameter-efficient Transfer Learning, Multi-modal Large Language Model
- Director: Prof. Huchuan Lu

Dalian University of Technology (DUT), Dalian

Sep. 2018 — Jun. 2021

M.E. in Information and Communication Engineering

- Thesis: Person Re-Identification, Image-text Retrieval, Video-text Retrieval
- Director: Prof. Huchuan Lu

Dalian University of Technology (DUT), Dalian

Sep. 2014 — Jun. 2018

B.E. in Electronic Information Engineering

• GPA: Top3% (School of Information and Communication Engineering)

Awards & Hornors

Awards

• Gold Award of the 9th Liaoning College students' 'Internet+' Competition

Liaoning Province, 2023

Hornors

• Excellent Graduate of Dalian City (Bachelor's degree)

Dalian City, 2018

• Excellent Graduate of Dalian University of Technology (Bachelor's degree)

DUT, 2018 Dalian City, 2016

Lingshui Scholarship (First Prize) (Top 5%)
China National Scholarship (Top 1%)

Ministry of Education, 2015

• Awarded Learning Excellence Award (First Prize) (Top 5%)

DUT, 2015/16

Publications

Conference Publications

1. Similarity Reasoning and Filtration for Image-Text Matching

<u>Haiwen Diao,</u> Ying Zhang, Lin Ma, Huchuan Lu

Conference on Artificial Intelligence (AAAI), 2021. (google citations: 170+) [Code]

Journal Publications

2. Plug-and-Play Regulators for Image-Text Matching

<u>Haiwen Diao</u>, Ying Zhang, Wei Liu, Xiang Ruan, Huchuan Lu IEEE Transactions on Image Processing (TIP), 2023. [Code]

Patents Declaration

1. An Image Retrieval Method and Related Device

Huchuan Lu, <u>Haiwen Diao</u>, Ying Zhang, Lin Ma CN111914113A, China, 2020.

Professional Services

Journal Reviewer:

IEEE Transactions on Image Processing

Conference Reviewer:

CVPR (2022 - 2024), ICCV (2023), ECCV (2022), AAAI (2023 - 2024)

References

• Prof. Huchuan Lu (Ph.D. Advisor)

School of Information and Communication Engineering

Dalian University of Technology (DLUT)

Dalian, Liaoning, 116024, China

Email: lhchuan@dlut.edu.cn

• Dr. Lin Ma (Industrial Director)

Meituan AI Lab

Chaoyang, Beijing, 100102, China

Email: forest.linma@gmail.com

• Dr. XinLong Wang (Industrial Director)

Beijing Academy of Artificial Intelligence (BAAI)

Haidian, Beijing, 100871, China

Email: wangxinlong@baai.ac.cn

• Dr. Ying Zhang (Industrial Director)

Tencent WeiXin Group (WXG)

Shenzhen, Guangdong 518000, China

Email: zydl0907@gmail.com

• Asst. Prof. Long Chen (Remote Director)

Hong Kong University of Science and Technology (HKUST)

Clear Water Bay, Kowloon, Hong Kong, 999077, China

Email: longchen@cse.ust.hk

• Ph.D. Bo Wan (Collaborator)

University of Leuven (KU Leuven)

Oude Markt 13, Leuven, 3000, Belgium

Email: bwan@esat.kuleuven.be